As a kid, I had two favorite movies.
Terminator 2: Judgement Day and that one
where Sinbad played a genie. Well,
yesterday, Google DeepMind released a
new AI model that's like if those two
movies had a baby. It's named Genie 3
and has the ability to create
controllable virtual worlds from a text
prompt and simulate them in real time at
720p resolution and 24 frames per
second. And we're not just talking about
video rendering here, but worlds with
actual physical properties that you can
interact with, like an openw world video
game. Genie is an AI system that
understands reality well enough to
simulate it. Think of it like the
inverse of perception. Instead of
understanding what it sees, it generates
what could be seen if it had eyeballs
like us. And that's a big deal because
it gives autonomous systems and robots
an unlimited number of simulated
environments for training. In today's
video, we'll take a closer look at Genie
along with two other big AI
announcements that you may have missed
if you blinked yesterday. It is August
6, 2025, and you're watching the code
report. Before we talk about Google's
Genie, OpenAI did something I thought I
would never see. They released an OpenAI
model with an Apache 2.0 license,
meaning you can use it freely to build a
billion-dollar business. GPTO OSS is a
model that's so good it approaches the
performance of other state-of-the-art
reasoning models like 03 while being
small enough to run on your laptop or
even your phone. I tried it out on O
Lama and while it's great to have
another open model, it still feels
overly censored and a little bit behind
Quen 3 in general intelligence. And with
smaller models, you get higher
hallucination rates, which is
understandable because you have to cut
out a lot of knowledge. That makes it
hard to use for any kind of serious
programming. But luckily, software
engineers also got a big upgrade
yesterday from Anthropic with the
release of Claude Opus 4.1. The upgraded
model made an improvement to its already
impressive software engineering bench
score. And supposedly this model is
supposed to be way better at multifile
code refactoring. And that's a big deal
because as your project grows larger,
the more useless AI becomes. But large
language models are like so boring in
2025. And the shiny new AI object for
today is something called a world model.
With Genie 3 being the frontier model
released by Google DeepMind yesterday,
tech influencers are calling it a
watershed moment that pushes us to the
brink of AGI. But remember, you should
never listen to tech influencers,
especially faceless AI powered YouTube
channels that are owned by private
equity. That being said, Genie 3 is
without exaggeration a watershed moment
that puts us dangerously close to
self-replicating genocidal machines by
giving robots an unlimited simulation
space. It generates realistic physical
environments with incredible
consistency. And what's especially weird
is that the consistency is an emergent
property, meaning the model just kind of
magically got better at keeping the
graphics consistent as it got bigger, as
opposed to being a deliberate change to
the algorithm implemented by
programmers. Google has been working on
these world models for a while, but
Genie 3 is the first one with an
interaction horizon that lasts multiple
minutes and that can generate
highresolution graphics in real time. It
can create both realistic and fictional
worlds from a simple text prompt while
also giving physical properties to
objects in that world that you can
interact with just like a video game.
It's a fun little toy for us humans, but
for robots, it provides an unlimited
training space to get better and better
at what they do. Humanoid robot tech is
right around the corner with Unitry
releasing the R1 for just $5,900 a few
weeks ago. And it won't be long before
robots like this are cooking our meals,
walking our dogs, and curing our
loneliness. If you want to get in on
this future though, you need to use the
right tools like Warp, the sponsor of
today's video. The CLI based AI tools
have been dominating headlines lately,
but Warp's agentic development
environment might be the most goatated
one yet. Its coding agent beat out
Claude Code and the Gemini CLI to land
the number one spot on the terminal
bench benchmark along with a top five
spot on SWE. And unlike other CLI tools,
Warp also gives you the key parts of the
IDE that you need to edit files, review
diffs, and ship productionready code. It
also lets you run and manage multiple
files in parallel and is engineered for
deeper context and better planning with
full access to your stack and your
codebase embeddings. Warp is free to
use, but you can get access to one month
of their pro plan for just a dollar
using the code top agent. This has been
the code report. Thanks for watching and
I will see you in the next